So if I was to ask you
إذا أردت أن أسألكم
what the connection between
عن العلاقة بين
a bottle of Tide detergent and sweat was,
عبوة المنظف تايد والعرق
you'd probably think that's the easiest question
فستعتقدون بأنه سؤال سهل جداً
that you're going to be asked in Edinburgh all week.
حتى تُسألونه في أدنبرة طوال اﻷسبوع.
But if I was to say that they're both examples
لكن اذا أخبرتكم بأنه هذه العلاقة مثال
of alternative or new forms of currency
لوجه بديل وجديد للعملات
in a hyperconnected, data-driven global economy,
في إقتصاد عالمي متصل ومعتمد على البيانات والمعلومات
you'd probably think I was a little bit bonkers.
فستظنون بأنها مزحة غريبة
But trust me, I work in advertising.
لكن ثقو بي، فأنا أعمل في مجال اﻹعلانات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I am going to tell you the answer,
وسأخبركم بالجواب
but obviously after this short break.
ولكن بكل تأكيد بعد فاصلٍ إعلاني قصير
So a more challenging question is one
حسناً، هناك سؤال أكثر تحدي
that I was asked, actually, by one of our writers
سألني إياه أحد كُتّابنا
a couple of weeks ago, and I didn't know the answer:
منذ بضعة أسابيع، ولكني لم أعرف الجواب
What's the world's best performing currency?
ماهي أفضل عملة يُتداول بها عالمياً؟
It's actually Bitcoin.
إنها Bitcoint
Now, for those of you who may not be familiar,
حسناً، إذا كنتم لاتعرفون Bitcoin
Bitcoin is a crypto-currency, a virtual currency, synthetic currency.
فهي عملة تشفير و إفتراضية
It was founded in 2008 by this anonymous programmer
تم إنشاؤها عام 2008 من قبل مبرمج مجهول
using a pseudonym Satoshi Nakamoto.
إستعمل إسم مستعار يدعى ساتوشي ناكاموتو
No one knows who or what he is.
لا أحد يعرف من يكون
He's almost like the Banksy of the Internet.
يشبه إلى حد ما بانكسي (رسام جرافيتي مجهول)
And I'm probably not going to do it proper service here,
غالباً لن أقدم الخدمة هنا
but my interpretation of how it works is that
ولكن تفسيري لطريقة عملها
Bitcoins are released through this process of mining.
أن Bitcoin أصدرت خلال عملية التنقيب المعلوماتي
So there's a network of computers that are challenged
حيث هناك شبكة من أجهزة الكمبيوتر التي تواجه تحديات
to solve a very complex mathematical problem
لحل مشكلة رياضية معقدة جدا
and the person that manages to solve it first gets the Bitcoins.
والشخص الذي يتمكن أولاً من حل المشكلة يحصل على Bitcoins
And the Bitcoins are released,
لذلك أُصدرت Bitcoins
they're put into a public ledger called the Blockchain,
وتم وضعها في منصة عامة تُدعى Blockchain
and then they float, so they become a currency,
فأشتهرت وأصبحت عملة يتداول بها
and completely decentralized, that's the sort of
عملة غير مركزية وهذا يعتبر
scary thing about this, which is why it's so popular.
مريب نوعاً ما، لذلك أشتهرت
So it's not run by the authorities or the state.
فهي لا تدار من قبل أي جهة محددة
It's actually managed by the network.
بل تدار من قبل الشبكة
And the reason that it's proved very successful
وهذا من أسباب نجاحها
is it's private, it's anonymous, it's fast, and it's cheap.
تمتاز بالخصوصية وخفية وسريعة ورخيصة
And you do get to the point where there's some wild fluctuations with Bitcoin.
تَمُرُّ العملة ببعض التقلبات في قيمتها
So in one level it went from something like 13 dollars
في بعض اﻷحيان قد تتحول 13 دولار
to 266, literally in the space of four months,
إلى 266 دولار خلال 4 أشهر
and then crashed and lost half of its value in six hours.
وبعدها تخسر نصف قيمتها في غضون 6 ساعات
And it's currently around that kind of
وهي حالياً على هذا المنوال
110 dollar mark in value.
حوالي بما قيمته 110 دولار
But what it does show is that it's sort of gaining ground,
ولكنها بدأت في طور الثبات واﻹستقرار
it's gaining respectability.
وكسب الثقة
You get services, like Reddit and Wordpress
فعند إستعمالك خدمات كلٍ من Reddit و Wordpress
are actually accepting Bitcoin as a payment currency now.
سيقبلون Bitcoint كوسيلة دفع معتمدة
And that's showing you that people
وهذا يظهر لك أن الناس
are actually placing trust in technology,
يثقون حقاً في التقنية
and it's started to trump and disrupt
وعلى صعيد آخر بدأت
and interrogate traditional institutions
في أخذ البساط من المؤسسات المالية التقليدية
and how we think about currencies and money.
في تغيير نظرتنا إلى العملات واﻷموال
And that's not surprising, if you think about
وهذا ليس بمستغرب إذا فكرت به
the basket case that is the E.U.
كمثال النكسة اﻹفتصادية في أوروبا
I think there was a Gallup survey out recently
كان هناك مؤخراً إستبيان لغالوب
that said something like, in America,
عن أمريكا يقول بأن
trust in banks is at an all-time low, it's something like 21 percent.
الثقة في البنوك بشكلٍ عام منخفظة وتصل إلى 21٪
And you can see here some photographs from London
ويمكن رؤية بعض الصور من لندن
where Barclays sponsored the city bike scheme,
حيث تقوم مؤسسة باركليز بدعم مخطط الدراجات الهوائية بالمدينة
and some activists have done some nice piece
وبعض النشطاء عملو شيئًا يستحق الذكر
of guerrilla marketing here and doctored the slogans.
من خلال الحملات التسويقية وبعض الشعارات
"Sub-prime pedaling." "Barclays takes you for a ride."
كمثال "باركبيز تأخذك في جولة"
These are the more polite ones I could share with you today.
وهذه من ألطف العبارات
But you get the gist, so people have really started
مما لاحظتم أن الناس
to sort of lose faith in institutions.
بدأو بفقد الثقة في المنظمات
There's a P.R. company called Edelman,
هناك شركة علاقات عامة تدعى
they do this very interesting survey every year
تُجري بحثاً سنوياً
precisely around trust and what people are thinking.
عن الثقة ومايدور في أذهان الناس
And this is a global survey, so these numbers are global.
على مستوى عالمي
And what's interesting is that you can see that
ومما وجدوه أنّ
hierarchy is having a bit of a wobble,
القوة المعتمدة على المركزية بدأت بالتذبذب
and it's all about heterarchical now,
لصالح القوة الغير مركزية
so people trust people like themselves more
لذلك بدأ الناس يثقوا ببعضهم البعض
than they trust corporations and governments.
أكثر من ثقتهم بالحكومات والمنظمات
And if you look at these figures for the more developed markets
واذا أخذت نظرة على إحصائيات الدول المتقدمة
like U.K., Germany, and so on, they're actually much lower.
كالمملكة المتحدة وألمانيا ستجد أن النسب أقل بكثير
And I find that sort of scary.
وهذا يثير الريبة
People are actually trusting businesspeople
فالناس في الحقيقة يثقون برجال الأعمال
more than they're trusting governments and leaders.
أكثر من ثقتهم بالحكومات والسياسيين
So what's starting to happen, if you think about money,
لذلك على صعيد الأموال يمكنك التفكير
if you sort of boil money down to an essence,
بنفس الشيء
it is literally just an expression of value, an agreed value.
فالأموال تعبر عن قيمة تم الاتفاق عليها
So what's happening now, in the digital age,
فما يحصل الان في العالم الرقمي
is that we can quantify value in lots of different ways
يتم الاتفاق على أشياء متعددة للتعبير عن القيمة
and do it more easily,
وبشكل أسهل
and sometimes the way that we quantify those values,
وأحياناً من خلال حسابنا لهذه القيمة
it makes it much easier
يصبح الوضع أسهل بكثير
to create new forms and valid forms of currency.
لإنشاء أشكال متعددة للعملة
In that context, you can see that networks like Bitcoin
وفي هذا السياق يمكنك ملاحظة Bitcoin
suddenly start to make a bit more sense.
بدأت في أخذ حيز معتبر
So if you think we're starting to question
فإذا أردت السؤال
and disrupt and interrogate what money means,
عما تعنيه الاموال حقاً
what our relationship with it is, what defines money,
وعن علاقتنا بها، وما يحددها
then the ultimate extension of that is,
سيقودنا التفكير الى سؤال
is there a reason for the government to be in charge
هل هناك سبب لتحكم الحكومات
of money anymore?
بالأموال؟
So obviously I'm looking at this through a marketing prism,
سأنظر الى هذا الموضوع من نظرة تسويقية
so from a brand perspective,
من نظرة العلامة التجارية
brands literally stand or fall on their reputations.
حيث العلامة التجارية تٌحدد بالسمعة
And if you think about it, reputation has now become a currency.
واذا فكرت تجد أن السمعة أصبحت عملة
You know, reputations are built on trust,
تٌبنى على الثقة
consistency, transparency.
الثبات والشفافية
So if you've actually decided that you trust a brand,
لذلك إذا قررت أن تثق بعلامة تجارية
you want a relationship, you want to engage with the brand,
فستجد نفسك على علاقة بهذه العلامة
of currency.
العملة
So you think about loyalty.
واذا فكرت الآن بولاء العملاء
Loyalty essentially is a micro-economy.
الذي يعتبر ضرورة إقتصادية
You think about rewards schemes, air miles.
فكر بالمكافآت وأميال السفر المجانية
The Economist said a few years ago that
يخبرنا الإقتصاديون أنه خلال السنوات الماضية
there are actually more unredeemed air miles in the world
عدد الأميال المجانية الغير المستخدمة في العالم
than there are dollar bills in circulation.
أكثر من سندات الدولار في التداول
You know, when you are standing in line in Starbucks,
وعندما تقف في طابور مقهى ستاربكس
30 percent of transactions in Starbucks on any one day
ستجد أن نسبة العمليات في اليوم الواحد
are actually being made with Starbucks Star points.
تتم من خلال بطاقات ستاربكس
So that's a sort of Starbucks currency
وهذه تعتبر عملة خاصة لستاربكس
staying within its ecosystem.
وعلى نفس السياق
And what I find interesting is that Amazon
ماوجدته مثيراً حول أمازون
has recently launched Amazon coins.
أنها أصدرت برنامج يُدعى نقاط أمازون
So admittedly it's a currency at the moment that's purely for the Kindle.
وتوقعي أن نقاط أمازون سيكون عُملة خاصة لجهاز أمازون كندل
So you can buy apps and make purchases within those apps,
مما يمكنك من شراء تطبيقات وغيرها
but you think about Amazon,
لكن اذا فكرت في امازون
you look at the trust barometer that I showed you
فأنت تنظر إلى مقياس الثقة الذي عرضته
where people are starting to trust businesses,
من أن الناس بدأو يثقون بالشركات
especially businesses that they believe in and trust
خصوصاً الشركات التي يثقون بها
more than governments.
أكثر من ثقتهم بالحكومات
So suddenly, you start thinking,
لذلك فكر
well Amazon potentially could push this.
أن أمازون من الممكن
It could become a natural extension,
ان تتحقق تطور من خلال نقاط امازون
that as well as buying stuff --
لتتمكن خلال من شراء الحاجيات
take it out of the Kindle -- you could buy books, music,
فتأخذ النقاط من أمازون لشراء الكتب والموسيقى
real-life products, appliances and goods and so on.
والمنتجات الاخرى كالادوات الكهربائية وغيرها
And suddenly you're getting Amazon, as a brand,
وسيصبح حينها أمازون كعلامة تجارية
is going head to head with the Federal Reserve
نِداً للإحتياطي الفيدرالي
in terms of how you want to spend your money,
في تحديد طريقة صرفك لاموالك
what money is, what constitutes money.
وماهي الاموال وعلى ماذا تحتوي
And I'll get you back to Tide, the detergent now,
وبالعودة الى عبوة تايد
as I promised.
كما وعدتكم
This is a fantastic article I came across in New York Magazine,
وجدت مقالاً في مجلة نيويورك
where it was saying that drug users across America
يقول ان متعاطيِّ المخدرات في أمريكا
are actually purchasing drugs
يقومون بشراء المخدرات
with bottles of Tide detergent.
مع عبوة المنظف تايد
So they're going into convenience stores,
من خلال ذهابهم الى السوبر الماركت
stealing Tide,
وسرقة تايد
and a $20 bottle of Tide
فعبوة تايد ذات 20 دولار
is equal to 10 dollars of crack cocaine or weed.
تعادل 10 دولار من الحشيش أو الكوكايين
And what they're saying, so some criminologists
ومن خلال نظر علماء الجريمة
have looked at this and they're saying, well, okay,
تم اﻹستنتاج
It's 50 percent above the category average.
ويصنف أفضل من بقية منتجات المنظفات
It's infused with a very complex cocktail of chemicals,
حيث يتكون من مواد كيميائية معقدة
so it smells very luxurious and very distinctive,
لذلك يمتلك رائحة مميزة
and, being a Procter and Gamble brand,
وكونه أحد منتجات شركة بروكتل و قامبل
it's been supported by a lot of mass media advertising.
تم عمل له الكثير من الإعلانات
so they have this in their neural pathways.
بإختيارهم منتجهم المفظل
When they spot Tide, there's a shortcut.
عندما يخطر على بالهم
They say, that is trust. I trust that. That's quality.
بقولهم أنهم يثقون بجودة تايد
So it becomes this unit of currency,
لذلك يصبح ذلك عملة محددة
which the New York Magazine described
وصفت مجلة نيويورك ذلك
as a very oddly loyal crime wave, brand-loyal crime wave,
بأنها موجة لجريمة الوفاء الغريبة، موجة جريمة الوفاء للعلامة التجارية
and criminals are actually calling Tide "liquid gold."
المجرمون يطلقون على تايدـ في الواقع "السائل الذهبي"
Now, what I thought was funny was the reaction
الآن، ما اعتقدت أنه مضحك هو رد الفعل
They said, obviously tried to dissociate themselves from drugs,
فقد قال، نائيا بالشركة عن المخدرات على ما يبدو
and that's the value of the brand has stayed consistent." (Laughter)
وهو أن قوة العلامة التجارية ظلت قوية." (ضحك)
Which backs up my point and shows he didn't even
وهو ما يدعم وجهة نظري ويبين أنه حتى لم
break a sweat when he said that.
يرهقه قول ذلك.
So that brings me back to the connection with sweat.
وهذا يعيدني إلى ما يتعلق بالإرهاق.
In Mexico, Nike has run a campaign recently
في المكسيك، قامت شركة نايك بإدارة حملة مؤخرا
called, literally, Bid Your Sweat.
تسمى، حرفيا ارهق نفسك.
So you think about,
لذلك تفكر حول الأمر
these Nike shoes have got sensors in them,
أحذية نايك تلك لديها مجسات
or you're using a Nike FuelBand
أو أنك ترتدي حذاء نايك الـ فويلباند
that basically tracks your movement, your energy,
والذي يتعقب حركتك، وطاقتك،
your calorie consumption.
وحرقك لسعراتك الحرارية.
And what's happening here, this is where you've actually
والذي يحدث هنا هو، هذا ما بالفعل ما قد
elected to join that Nike community. You've bought into it.
انتخبك لتنضم لمجتمع نايك. لقد اشتريت نفسك لتدخله.
They're not advertising loud messages at you,
إنهم لا يصرخون بوجهك برسالة إعلانية،
and that's where advertising has started to shift now
وهنا حيث بدأت نبرة الإعلانية في التحول
is into things like services, tools and applications.
لأشياء كالخدمة، والأدوات والتطبيقات.
So Nike is literally acting as a well-being partner,
فنايك تتصرف كأنها شريك في الصحة،
a health and fitness partner and service provider.
شريك اللياقة الصحة ومقدم الخدمة.
So what happens with this is they're saying, "Right,
فالذي يحث بذلك هو أنهم يقولون، "حسنا،
you have a data dashboard. We know how far you've run,
لديك لوحة عرض البيانات. نحن نعلم كم المسافة التي عدوتها،
how far you've moved, what your calorie intake, all that sort of stuff.
لأي مدى تحركت، وقدر السعرات الرارية التي تتناولها، ومعلومات من هذا القبيل.
What you can do is, the more you run, the more points you get,
والذي يمكنك فعله هو، كلما عدوت أكثر، حصلت على نقاط أكثر،
and we have an auction where you can buy Nike stuff
ولدينا مزاد حيث يمكنك شراء منتجات أخرى لنايك
but only by proving that you've actually used the product to do stuff."
ولكن فقط بإثباتك أن استخدمت المنتج بالفعل."
And you can't come into this. This is purely
ولا يمكنك الوصول لذلك. هذا خاص فقط
for the community that are sweating
بذلك المجتمع الذي يرهق نفسه
using Nike products. You can't buy stuff with pesos.
باستخدامه لمنتجات نايك. لا يمكنك شراء أشياء بالبيزوز (عملة بأمريكا اللاتينية)
This is literally a closed environment, a closed auction space.
هذه بيئة مغلقة كما تعنيه الكلمة، مزاد معلق.
In Africa, you know, airtime has become
في أفريقيا، مدة البث الإعلامية أصبحت
literally a currency in its own right.
عملة في حد ذاتها.
People are used to, because mobile is king,
الناس اعتادت على، ولأن الهاتف المحمول شيء أساسي،
they're very, very used to transferring money,
فهم اعتادوا كليا على تحويل الأموال،
making payments via mobile.
ودفع التزاماتهم المالية عبر الهاتف المحمول.
And one of my favorite examples from a brand perspective
وواحدا من أمثلتي المفضلة، من وجهة النظر المتعلقة بالعلامة التجارية
going on is Vodafone, where, in Egypt,
في فودافون، حيث هناك الكثير في مصر
lots of people make purchases in markets
يقومون بعمليات شراء من أسواق
and very small independent stores.
ومتاجر صغيرة ومستقلة.
Loose change, small change is a real problem,
عدم إدراك التقدير، التغيير البسيط هو مشكلة حقيقية،
and what tends to happen is you buy a bunch of stuff,
وما يحدث غالبا هو أنك تشتري مجموعة من الأشياء،
you're due, say,
تكون مستحق، لنقول
10 cents, 20 cents in change.
10 قروش، و 20 قرش وبالمقابل
The shopkeepers tend to give you things like an onion
يعطونك بالمتجر أشياء كـ بصلة
or an aspirin, or a piece of gum,
أو أسبيرين، أو قطعة علكة،
because they don't have small change.
بسبب أن ليس لديهم فكة.
So when Vodafone came in and saw this problem,
فعندما جاءت فودافون ورأت تلك المشكلة،
this consumer pain point, they created
نقطة الألم للمستهلك، التي ابتكروها
some small change which they call Fakka,
بعض القيم النقدية الصغيرة والتي يسمونها "فكة"
which literally sits and is given
والتي تحصى وتعطى
by the shopkeepers to people,
من البائع بالمتجر للناس،
and it's credit that goes straight onto their mobile phone.
وهي رصيد يذهب مباشرة لخطوطهم الهاتفية.
So this currency becomes credit, which again,
فتتحول العملة لرصيد، والتي مرة أخرى،
is really, really interesting.
تعد بالفعل أمرا مشوق،ا حقا.
And we did a survey that backs up the fact that,
وقمنا باحصاء ليدعم الحقيقة التي،
you know, 45 percent of people
أن 45% من الناس
in this very crucial demographic in the U.S.
في هذا التوزيع الديموغرافي في الولايات المتحدة
were saying that they're comfortable using
كانوا يقولون أنهم مرتاحون باستخدامهم
an independent or branded currency.
للعملات المستقلة أو المرتبطة بشركة معينة.
So that's getting really interesting here,
فهذا أصبح مشوقا جدا هنا،
a really interesting dynamic going on.
حقا، تفاعل مشوق حادث.
And you think, corporations
وتعتقد أن، الشركات
should start taking their assets and thinking of them
يجب أن تأخذ أصولها وتفكر فيها
in a different way and trading them.
بطريقة مختلفة وتقوم بالإتجار فيها.
And you think, is it much of a leap?
وهل تعتقد، أن ذلك يعد طفرة كبيرة؟
It seems farfetched, but when you think about it,
تبدو بعيدة المنال، ولكن بالتفكير بها،
in America in 1860,
في أمريكا سنة 1860،
there were 1,600 corporations issuing banknotes.
كانت هناك 1600 شركة تصدر الأوراق النقدية.
There were 8,000 kinds of notes in America.
كان هناك 8000 نوع من الأوراق النقدية بالولايات المتحدة.
And the only thing that stopped that,
والشيء الوحيد الذي أوقف ذلك،
the government controlled four percent of the supply,
أن الحكومة تحكمت بـ4% من العرض،
and the only thing that stopped it
والشيء الوحيد الذي أوقف هذا
was the Civil War breaking out,
هو اندلاع الحرب الأهلية،
and the government suddenly wanted to take control of the money.
وأرادت الحكومة فجأة أن تتحكم بالأموال.
So what I'm going to ask is, basically,
فالذي سأسأله أساسا هو،
is history repeating itself?
هل يكرر التاريخ نفسه؟
Is technology making paper money feel outmoded?
هل تسببت التقنية في جعل طباعة الأموال أمرا بال؟
Are we decoupling money from the government?
هل نقوم بفك الصلة بين الأموال و الحكومة؟
You know, you think about, brands are starting to fill the gaps.
تعلم، لو تلاحظ، العلامات التجارية بدأت في سد الثغور.
Corporations are filling gaps that governments can't afford to fill.
الشركات تسد الثغور التي لا تتحمل الحكومة تكلفة سدها.
So I think, you know, will we be standing on stage
فأعتقد أننا سنقف على خشبة المسرح
buying a coffee -- organic, fair trade coffee -- next year
ونشتري القهوة -- قهوة حيوية، بمقايضة عادلة --في العام المقبل
using TED florins or TED shillings?
مستخدمين فلورينات تيد وشيلناته؟
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)